No, I haven't lost my mind. I'm going to
be showing you some alarming data on
exercise and more plaque being in the
arteries. Not just in one study, but
multiple. That said, though, before
someone comments next, they'll say that
water is dehydrating or something else
snarky, watch the whole video. There's a
lot to get into and it'll make sense in
the end without upending foundational
truths about health. If we look at one
of these studies and we pop open the
data, we're looking at the prevalence of
having one or more plaques in the
arteries between those who've been
exercising their entire lives defined as
before 30 years of age and then those
picking up exercise later in life, so
after 30, and the control group. By
comparison, shockingly, those who
exercised for the longest period of time
had more arterial plaque. But that's not
the end of it because it's not just uh
about the presence of plaque. It's also
about the type of plaque found in your
blood vessels. There's three distinct
types. So calcified plaque,
non-calcified plaque, and mixed plaque.
The most dangerous as in the most likely
to break and cause downstream issues is
mixed and non-calcified plaque. So when
we look at that, we see a huge increase
in those who have been exercising their
entire lives. Like I said, I was not
lying to you. And I'm also not insane.
This is in addition in people with no
previous history of cardiovascular
disease that were leaner than the
control group. So we're looking at
people who exercise long-term having
more arterial plaque and more of the
dangerous type of arterial plaque. That
raises the question of uh what's leading
to this accelerated plaque growth and is
it all exercise or select? Well, a
follow-up study recently released that
tried to find out if it was the duration
of exercise or the intensity of exercise
that tracked with these platforming
results. Now, I've transformed the data
here for you for the duration of
exercise with the left side being the
lowest duration up to the highest. And
we're again sticking with the prevalence
of plaque in the arteries. The higher
the lines go, the worse the results. I
don't need to really spell it out for
you. Probably as duration increases,
more plaque is related. Is this what we
also find with the intensity of
exercise? I'll keep the duration data up
and move the intensity data on screen
here. All you need to ask yourself is,
do they look like they're trending the
same direction? The answer is no. This
tells us that the plaque is only
increased with added duration, not with
intensity alone. But as bonkers as this
question might be, does more plaque
necessarily mean more cardiovascular
events like heart attacks, strokes, and
death? The obvious would be to say uh
well, duh.
Is this guy serious?
We're always trying to avoid plaque
because it is the major driver of
cardiovascular disease. Now, you'd be
surprised actually. There are studies
that look at very physically fit people
and track the relationship between
plaque and cardiovascular disease. And
in these studies, they do not find a
relationship between increased physical
activity, so more plaque, and
cardiovascular mortality. To say that
differently, they confirm that there's
signs of more plaque in people who are
very physically active, but it doesn't
translate to cardiovascular mortality.
The kicker here is, however, that they
are focused exclusively on calcified
plaque. Remember the distinction between
the three, so calcified, non-calcified,
and mixed plaque. Calcified is the least
problematic. That means that while these
kinds of studies are informative, they
aren't absolving us of being worry-f
free here. Still, we can at least say
that although people who are very
physically active have greater
relationship with more calcified plaque,
there's no additional increased risk of
cardiovascular death. Plus, there's a
major weakness in many of these studies
released on exercise and plaque that
these new worrying studies actually fix,
making them possibly better. And
remember when we looked at the data on
duration of exercise and greater plaque.
This one, that data was collected
objectively, meaning that participants
had devices on that tracked their
exercise. However, many studies use
self-report, which is in in the exercise
literature is apparently not that
accurate. And the same researchers
quantified the plaque in the arteries.
Exactly the same measure, but they use
the self-report data instead of the
wearable device data, the objective
data. And let me put both of them up for
you. Notice anything?
Yeah, they don't look the same, which is
exactly the problem. The more exact
measurement technique indicates
relationship with more plaque, but the
self-report data does not give the same
story. This is a perfect illustration of
using the most exact techniques where
feasible can make a world of difference
because we'd miss this relationship with
arterial plaque. So, after having said
all of that, is that it? Are we now
flipping the script on exercise? Is
exercise a negative for heart health? or
are there maybe I don't know maybe some
nuances here to be had. Before I package
this all together with some important
factors that will change your
perspective here, let me point out that
I'm also covering more on calcified
plaque as well as going over a
particular formula that helps calculate
if you'd be considered higher risk of
developing plaques based on your
exercise and much more data on physical
activity and different forms of uh heart
disease. That's all covered in my
extended analysis of this video that
you're watching. It's available as a
physionic insider along with all of
these perks right here. If you're
interested, then check out the insiders
using the link in the description. Now,
there are four factors that I'd like to
bring to your attention that will shift
our perspective here. So, one is a minor
factor, I think, is that none of these
studies account for factors like
nutrition. I don't think this is as big
a deal here. simply because the defining
feature of this platforming relationship
is constrained to exercise. So would we
expect major differences in factors like
nutrition between those who focus on
long duration exercise versus those that
focus on intensity to explain the
difference between the two. Plus
mediating factors meaning factors that
actually cause the plaque were accounted
for like cholesterol, blood pressure,
age, blood sugar and more. Still, this
type of associative study could still be
affected by some unexplained factor. As
one quick additional mention, the whole
study was in men. So, could this be
unique to men? I doubt it, but possibly.
Number two, remember when I showed you
this? Remember how I briefly described
this group as the control group? Well,
these people weren't your normal control
group used in many other studies. They
were also active, lightly active, but
active. This revelation alone is going
to change our interpretation
significantly, which I'll get to. Number
three, while current studies indicate
that exercise reduces the risk of
cardiovascular disease events and death,
none of these studies measure these
outcomes in people who have been
exercising their entire lives. And while
we saw one study indicating no risk for
people with higher calcium, no studies
have looked at the same highly active
people and the relationship with soft
plaque. This also doesn't account for
the fact that there are many of these
studies may be using self-report for
measures of exercise which as we saw may
be inaccurate. That brings me to my
fourth point that ties into the others.
Another measure was to look at stenosis,
which is the amount of narrowing or
blocking of the artery lumen, the uh
open section of the artery that allows
blood to pass through it. Now, check
this out. We're measuring the prevalence
again. But looking at the arteries with
over 50% blockage, does that seem
comforting to you? I wouldn't feel all
that comfortable, and that's for sure.
So, a lot scary, but let me break this
down into actionable takeaways because
the message here isn't that exercise is
bad for you or bad for your
cardiovascular health. As odd as that
might sound having gone over all the
data that we just did, there's a lot
more here that we need to investigate.
But as it stands, and even the
researchers point this out, exercise is
good for you and is encouraged for heart
health. However, the amount of exercise
is being called into question. Is more
always better? The issue is that we're
focusing on plaque, which certainly
doesn't sound good, but we don't have
any good data on actual outcomes, which
would be honestly more telling. It's
possible that plaque is increased, but
some other factors are improved to a
point that there's a net benefit on the
outcomes. Honestly, I'd be puzzled by
that, but it's possible at this point
considering that there's a lack of
outcome data. Still, even with that
uncertainty, we can focus in on that
control group, the group that was
lightly active. That means that there's
decent evidence that light duration
endurance exercise up to three hours per
week is low risk and likely a benefit
over a lifetime. There is less certainty
scaling up from there, though. The high
volume exercise was linked to increased
amounts of all forms of arterial plaque
averaged around triple that amount of
work. So around 10 hours of endurance
exercise per week. If that higher volume
translates to actual higher risk of
cardiovascular events and death is
currently unknown. So if you go for a
jog a few days a week, this does not
apply to you. If you run marathons and
triathlons, this probably does apply to
you. And scales in between there. If you
have been endurance exercising heavily
your entire life, this definitely
applies to you, too. But again, we don't
know the end result, just that there's
an associated unsettling increase in
arterial plaque. And since someone will
ask, none of this applies to resistance
training. In short, simple terms,
exercise, just not too much exercise.
And even if you choose to do much more
than the average, we're not even sure
yet if it translates into negative
outcomes. So, it's on you to consider
the risk and reward. In fact, speaking
to exercise and plaque, there's even
studies indicating that exercise can
reverse plaque. Don't worry, it does not
contradict with what we went over here.
Check it out right here. I hope this
didn't scare you off from endurance
training. It shouldn't. Thanks for
tuning in. Catch you in the next one.